# Victor Danilchenko

4 Willimansett st. South Hadley, MA 01075 (413) 420 3557 victor@danilchenko.net

**OBJECTIVE:** Senior technical position where my diverse background and experience will allow me to make the world a better place and engage in creative technical pursuits while delivering value to the enterprise.

#### **PRECIS**

I am a "full-stack" solution and enterprise architect with a wide array of both theoretical and practical knowledge. I am extremely self-motivated, capable of carrying a task from conception and specification through architecture, implementation, and operationalization. I have experience leading technical development of complex IT, IoT, and enterprise projects.

Possessing proficiency with a broad array of environments and technologies, as well as experience with technical architecture and architectural processes, I can leverage my excellent problem-solving and communication skills towards addressing a wide variety of problems, and readily translate between technical requirements, business & enterprise strategy, and non-technical user needs.

As a part of my work and a matter of personal interest, I also participate in, and lead, various research, invention, and international standardization activities.

## **SYSTEMS & PLATFORMS**

Operating systems: UNIX, Windows, Mac OS/X

Cloud computing platforms: Azure, AWS

## **SOFTWARE TECHNOLOGIES**

Software Stacks and Frameworks: .NET, Ajax, Rack, Django, LAMP, Mason, Flash, Cocoa

**Programming languages:** JavaScript, C#, Ruby, Perl, PHP, ActionScript, C++, Objective-C, C, Lisp, ML, Pascal, Fortran, Basic, Assembler (PC), Bourne Shell, C Shell, JCL

Database technologies: SQL, NoSQL, Dbase IV, POET

**Software and development paradigms:** IoT, IIoT, Agile, DevOps, REST, multi-tier architecture, microservice architecture

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- V. Danilchenko, M. Theobald, D. Cohen, "Bootstrapping security configuration for IoT devices on networks with TLS inspection", IEEE GlobeCom 2019 workshops. Accepted for publication.
- C. El Kaed, V. Danilchenko, F. Delpech, J. Brodeur, "Linking an Asset and a Domain Specific Ontology for a Simple Asset TimeSeries Application", IEEE Big Data 2018 workshops.
- A. Mouaddib, S. Zilberstein, V. Danilchenko, "New Directions in Modeling and Control of Progressive Processing", ECAI 1998.
- S. Zilberstein, E. Hansen, V. Danilchenko, "Anytime Heuristic Search: First Results", Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research 1998.

## **PATENTS**

- V. Danilchenko, Dan Cohen, "Security Context Distribution Service", US Patent Application PCT/US20/15667, filed January 2020. Patent pending.
- V. Danilchenko et al., "Systems and methods for dynamic ontology data operation", US Patent Application PCT/US19/55463, filed October 2019. Patent pending.

- V. Danilchenko, T. Whitehill, "Distributed standards registry for cloud computing environments", US Patent Application PCT/US19/35836, filed June 2019. Patent pending.
- V. Danilchenko, T. Whitehill, C. EL Kaed, "Semantic meta federation broker for cloud environments", US Patent Application PCT/US19/26323, filed April 2019. Patent pending.
- V. Danilchenko, T. Whitehill, "Systems and methods of a progressive cloud based architecture", US Patent Application PCT/US19/23879, filed March 2019. Patent pending.

#### **PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS**

TOGAF 9 Certified

MCSE Cloud Platform & Infrastructure

#### STANDARDS BODIES PARTICIPATION

IEEE P2301 working group: Cloud Profiles

IEEE P2302 working group: Intercloud Interoperability and Federation

ISO/IEC JTC1 sub-committee 38: Cloud Computing and Distributed Platforms

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

2016-Present **Senior Principal IoT Solution Architect**, Schneider Electric Inc., Digital Services Factory group, IoT Digital Transformation initiative

- Developed capability-centric IoT reference architecture
- Engaged with other Business Units to guide digitalization of existing products and services
- Initiated engagement process revision and update to better align it with the Enterprise Architecture paradigm
- Designed and then taught a series of training courses ("EcoStructure Technology Platform Bootcamp") to corporate locations around the globe
- Provided cloud (esp. Azure), IoT, and IIoT architectural expertise on multiple internal and customer-facing projects, including Industry 4.0 projects
- Guided the architecture cycle during multiple project engagements, and helped develop their architectural vision, content, and roadmap
- Worked with customers to identify, capture, and formalize business requirements
- Initiated, incubated, and architected new platform services and capabilities (LPWAN integration, Ontology platform, etc.)
- Initiated and/or drove multiple internal projects (Enterprise Architecture, documentation framework, architect working group, reference architecture, etc.)
- Generated Intellectual Property in the form of patents
- Authored and co-authored several published research articles

2012-2016 Solution Architect, Cimpress Inc., Learning & Knowledge Management group

- Oversaw a best-in-class knowledge base on MediaWiki platform, with over 200,000 articles (LAMP stack with PHP, on vSphere private cloud)
- Designed and led the implementation of high-availability clustering solution for the company-wide MediaWiki installation (load-balanced front end, MySQL cluster backend)
- Initiated and led through completion the migration of the LKM group's systems to a DevOps platform (Puppet), creating modular design with over 40 distinct system types
- Designed the LKM group's data access architecture (PHP+JS front end, Windows DFS backend, over 6 million documents)
- Initiated and led through completion the implementation of the group REST microservice platform (primarily JS, Bootstrap, Ruby, Sinatra, PHP, Apache)
- Mentored junior developers in proper software engineering and architecture processes and methodologies

# 2007-2012 Chief Technical Officer, AskOnline Inc.

• Led development effort for Software-as-a-Service solution that scaled to over 300,000

- users with a highly efficient infrastructure backend
- Was lead evaluator of third party systems, integrated several into the SaaS platform
- Oversaw platform integration with the clients' IT infrastructure (ADS, LDAP, SSO, etc.)
- Deployed the sales support infrastructure, oversaw its integration with third-party analytics services
- Managed customer support for hundreds of clients, achieving 99.99% uptime
- Performed product evangelism and outreach, attending multiple conferences

# 2005-2007 **Senior Software Engineer**, AskOnline Inc.

- Developed the SaaS application in the LAMP framework
- Was lead evaluator of third party systems, integrated several into the SaaS platform
- Integrated with the clients' IT infrastructure (ADS, LDAP, SSO, etc.)
- Administered the server backend for the SaaS deployment

# 1997-2005 **Software Specialist**, University of Massachusetts/Amherst

- Performed system administration for over 1800 Windows, Unix, and Mac clients and servers
- Performed end-user technical and operations support for a 400-member department, 45 research labs and administrative groups
- Primary in-house software developer for the department support group (5 applications)
- Implemented and supported various client/server technologies, such as LDAP, NIS, SQL, mail, web, and the SSL infrastructure

## 1996-1998 Research Assistant, RBR lab, Umass/Amherst

- Performed AI research at Resource-Bounded Reasoning Laboratory, coauthored and contributed to several publications
- Researched the theoretical aspects of 'anytime' algorithms

#### **EDUCATION**

2002 MS in Computer Science (Al concentration), University of Massachusetts

1996 BS in Computer Science, PACE University (Summa Cum Laude)

## **LANGUAGES**

English, Ukrainian, Russian (fluent), Spanish, French (intermediate)

# **REFERENCES**

Available upon request